原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/rLmpXgdgNZM.en
原视频发布日期：20200820
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
60 years ago this image was taken showing a Soviet airfield.
60年前拍下的这张照片显示的是一个苏联机场
This was the first photo ever taken by an operational spy satellite part of the CIA's Corona Program.
这是中情局(CIA)日冕计划中的间谍卫星拍摄的第一张照片
The Corona Program began in the late 1950s and operated until 1972.
日冕计划开始于20世纪50年代末 一直运行到1972年
It would be 20 years later when the US decided to start declassifying this imagery
在20年后(1992年) 美国才决定开始解密这些影像
because it was argued that
因为有人认为
this historic imagery might actually prove useful to researchers who were maybe studying geography.
那些地理学的研究人员实际上可以利用到这些历史图像
This program had started development in the understanding that
这个项目开始发展的原因是了解到
the U-2 spy planes were gonna have a limited life.
U-2间谍飞机的寿命是有限的
The truth was even the first U-2 spy planes flying over Russia had been tracked by radar
事实是 即使是第一架飞越俄罗斯的U-2间谍飞机 也被雷达追踪到了
and it was only a matter of time until they were shot down.
而击落U-2只是时间问题
But spacecraft flew above all these air defenses
但航天器飞行的高度超出了所有这些防空系统的能力(至少在当时)
and to a certain extent they flew above the political problems of flying your cameras over other countries.
在某种程度上 航天器的高度也超出了间谍飞机高度不足的政治问题
You know to a certain extent the Soviet Union by launching Sputnik first
你知道在某种程度上 苏联首先发射了斯普特尼克号
implicitly gave everybody else permission to fly their satellites over you know the Soviet Union.
暗示着允许其他人的卫星都可以在苏联上空飞行
The Corona satellites launched on board a Thor-Agena
日冕卫星是由雷神-阿金纳火箭发射的
that's a Thor booster with an Agena second stage
这枚火箭包含雷神助推器和阿金纳二级
but the Agena's second stage was actually much more complex.
但阿金纳二级实际上要复杂得多
It actually included sensors for attitude control.
其包括用于姿态控制的传感器
It provided power, communications
并提供动力和通讯
and the rest of the spacecraft could just be bolted on the front of it.
而航天器的其他部分可以直接固定在它的前面
It was a fully operating satellite bus.
这是一个可以完全(自主)运行的卫星总线
To operate as reconnaissance satellites
为了作为侦察卫星运行
the spacecraft had to be launched into polar orbits that they would fly over Russia.
航天器必须被发射到极轨道 这样它们就将飞越俄罗斯
That meant that they would be launched out of Vandenberg air force base.
这意味着航天器将从范登堡空军基地发射
Actually at the time when they were originally launched,
实际上 在最初发射的时候
they were launched from a place called Port(口胡) Arguello
是从Point Arguello(阿尔圭洛点)的地方发射的
which was essentially the southern portion of what is now Vandenberg.
这基本上是现在范登堡的南部地区
It was originally an navy facility and then it became part of the air force later.
它原本是海军设施 后来成为空军的一部分
The Agena used Nitric acid and UDMH as its propellant.
阿金纳使用硝酸和UDMH作为推进剂
The engine was originally developed for the Hustler missile
这台发动机最初是为B58盗贼轰炸机的导弹研制的
but it found more use as an Agena upper stage engine.
但它更多地被用作阿金纳上面级的发动机
Once in orbit it would orientate orient itself
一旦入轨 它就会自我定位
and this camera would scan a swath of land underneath it.
而这台相机将扫描它下面的一大片土地
The camera would essentially scan across onto a single piece of film
基本上就是把这些区域都扫描到一张胶片上
and it would have a very very long piece of film, thousands of feet long.
它有一段非常非常长的胶片 有上千米长
I think the early flight had about three thousand feet of film.
我认为早期的任务携带有914米长的胶片
And as the film moved to the camera,
当胶片移到相机上的时候
it would be loaded into a capsule or a bucket on the front of the spacecraft.
它将被装入航天器前部的一个胶囊或一个桶中
The operators would be able to send commands to the spacecraft to tell it when to take photographs
操作员将能够向航天器发送指令 告诉它何时拍照
so they would observe the satellite, figure out what orbit it was on
那么他们会监测卫星 计算出它在什么轨道上
and when it would be passing over areas of interest.
以及何时会经过感兴趣的区域
And then command it to take photos during those particular times.
然后控制它在这些特定的时间里拍摄照片
Once it had used up all its film, the spacecraft would orient itself to a return trajectory.
一旦用完了所有的胶卷 航天器就会定位至返回的轨道上
And then it would pop off that spacecraft on the front with the return bucket
接着在那个航天器的前端就会弹出返回桶
which would shoot away using a little solid rocket motor to slow its orbital velocity.
它会通过一个小的固体火箭发动机来减少其轨道速度
Apparently the real ones were spin stabilized and they had attitude gas you know thrusters.
很明显 现实中的返回舱会使用气体推进器进行自旋稳定
They would have a heat shield to protect them during re-entry.
在再入大气层的过程中 通过隔热板来保护返回舱
And once they were low enough in the atmosphere, a pressure sensor would trip.
一旦返回舱在大气层中到达了足够低的位置 压力传感器就会打开
And a parachute would deploy and the bucket would get pulled out
降落伞就会展开 而桶子就会被拉出来
and the bucket would then descend under a parachute towards the ground.
然后在降落伞的作用下 桶子会(缓慢)下降
But that wouldn't be the end of this experience
但这并不是整个流程的结束
because they wanted to make sure these capsules
因为他们想确保这些带有超级机密的胶卷的返回舱
were not recovered by anyone who shouldn't be finding this super classified film.
不会被不该拿到的人拿到
So the plan was that these would be descending over the ocean
所以计划里是 这些东西会降到海上
in the middle of nowhere where nobody could see what was going on.
在荒无人烟的地方 这样就没人能看到发生了什么
And before they touched the water, they would be captured by an aircraft in flight
在返回舱接触到水面之前 会被一架飞行中的飞机捕获
which was a pretty amazing concept. This didn't always happen.
这是一个相当惊人且罕见的概念
In fact the first successful recovery of any object from orbit was Corona Program flight number 13
事实上 第一次成功地从轨道上回收物体 是日冕计划的第13次飞行
where the capsule ended up going off course. It ended up over 100 miles away from the recovery aircraft.
在那次任务中 返回舱最终偏离了航线 离回收飞机有160多公里远
but the US navy did have a ship in the area
但美国海军确实有一艘船在该地区
and they were able to recover this highly important package.
(所以)之后他们就能回收这个非常重要的包裹
Now at this time this was still called the discoverer program officially.
那么 在这个时候 这仍然被正式地称为发现者计划
This was a cover story that was put together to hide the fact what they were really doing.
这是个编出来的幌子 打掩护用的
They told the press that they were sending biological samples into the into space and recovering them.
他们告诉媒体 这个任务是将生物样本送入太空并回收它们
And of course around exactly the same time Russia was doing almost the same thing.
当然 大约在同一时间 俄罗斯也在做几乎同样的事情
On August 19th I believe Belka and Strelka, two dogs went up into space
我记得在1960年8月19日 贝尔卡和斯特雷卡这两只狗进入了太空
on board an early prototype of the Vostok capsule and they did return.
这两只狗乘坐早期的东方号飞船并成功返回地球
And also curiously the Vostok capsule would also be adapted into a spy satellite by the Soviet Union.
而同样奇怪的是 东方号飞船也被苏联改造成过间谍卫星
And it's kind of amazing there wasn't much more than a week later
而且还有点神奇的是 不到一个星期之后
that Corona Program flight 14 was launched.
日冕计划就进行了第14次发射
And again they were trying to recover the capsule from the air.
同样 他们又尝试从空中回收返回舱
The aircraft tried to snag it a couple of times until they eventually got it.
飞机尝试了好几次才抓住
And this was the first recovery of photographic film from space.
这也是第一次从太空中回收相机胶卷
So this contained about 3000 feet of film showing areas of the Soviet Union
这里面保存着拍摄了苏联地区的大约914米的胶片
which had never been photographed by the US.
而且是从来没被美国人拍摄过的苏联地区
So you can see that the Corona Program was a huge step forward for the US intelligence services.
那么你会发现 日冕计划是美国情报部门向前迈出的一大步
They were finally able to see areas inside the USSR which were completely inaccessible.
他们终于能够看到苏联内部那些完全无法进入的地区
They found air bases that had never been seen previously and they were able to count things like missiles.
他们发现了以前从未见过的空军基地 而且他们还能够统计导弹数目之类的东西
The Corona satellites developed.
日冕卫星在此之后进行了不断地发展
There were at least you know four or five iterations of the Corona satellite design
其设计迭代了至少四五次
which added bigger and better cameras, improving the resolution over time.
其中增加了更大更好的相机 也就是随着时间的推移而提高了分辨率
The initial Corona satellites that recorded images had a resolution of about 40 feet. That's about 12 meters.
最初的日冕卫星记录图像的分辨率约为40英尺 也就是12米左右
But by the time the program had finished in 1972,
但到了1972年该计划结束的时候
they'd reduce the resolution or improve the resolution to about three feet or one meter.
他们就把分辨率数值降低或者说分辨率增强到三英尺或一米左右
This is the kind of thing you would see from early images.
这个程度差不多就是你从早期影像中得到的分辨率
But you know as time went on,
但你知道随着时间的推移
they got to they could pick out a lot more detail and can identify more stuff on the ground.
(分辨率得到了进一步提升) 他们可以找出更多的细节 并能识别地面上更多的东西
There were versions of the Corona satellite that was were able to generate resolutions of about 1 ft or 30 cm.
有一些版本的日冕卫星 能够产生大约1英尺或30厘米的分辨率
But to do that they had to narrow the observation track too much to be useful.
但要做到这一点 观测轨迹必须变窄(幅宽变小) 甚至达到无法实用化的程度
Corona was much better at looking at large wide areas
日冕卫星更擅长观察大面积的区域(更擅长在幅宽较大的情况下工作)
and the US actually developed other satellites in parallel
而美国实际上同时开发了其他卫星
that were able to look much more closely at specific areas.
那些卫星可以更仔细地观察特定区域
So all the US spy satellites are known as KH, Keyhole satellites
那么美国的间谍卫星都被称为KH 即锁眼卫星
and the first three Corona variants were KH-1, 2 and 3.
而前三个日冕卫星的种类是KH-1 2和3
The main difference here is that the Agena stage was swapped out with a larger one
这里的主要区别是增加了阿金纳上面级的规模
and there were minor improvements in the stability of the design.
并且在设计的稳定性上有小幅改进
The KH-4 delivered the first major upgrade.
KH-4进行了第一次重大升级
It had two cameras and one was angled slightly ahead of the track and one was aligned slightly behind.
它有两台相机 一台拍靠轨道位置稍微前面的地方 另一台拍稍微靠后的地方
The reason for this is they would photograph each set each area twice at a slightly different time.
这样做就可以在相差不大的时间内对同一个区域成像两次
And that gave them stereoscopic vision
这样就可以进行立体成像
so they could see objects coming up and they could estimate the height of things.
在同一个物体在(两个视野中)出现的时候 就可以估算出物体的高度
This was obviously great help for the analysts.
这显然对分析人员的帮助很大
The KH-4A added an improved J1 camera
KH-4A增加了一个改进型的J1相机
which brought the resolution from 7.5 meters to 2.75 meters
使得分辨率从7.5米下降到2.75米
and it also added a second return bucket so they could do two batches of imagery.
而且它还增加了第二个返回桶 所以他们可以在一次发射中做两批图像
This was the most launched version of Corona but it wasn't the last.
这是发射次数最多的日冕卫星版本 但不是最后一个
The final version would be 4B which added an even improved J3 camera
最终的版本是4B 它增加了一个更先进的J3相机
that brought the resolution down to 1.8 meters or about 6 feet.
使得分辨率降到了1.8米或6英尺左右
There were two other programs related to Corona. One was called Argon
还有两个与日冕有关的项目 一个叫氩气(KH-5)
and it was going to do world mapping at 140 meters resolution.
它将以140米的分辨率进行全球测绘
There were 12 of those flights and those were the first satellites to take satellite imagery of Antarctica.
有12次这样的飞行 这也是第一批拍摄南极洲卫星图像的卫星
And then there was Lanyard which was supposed to take much higher resolution imagery
然后是勋带(KH-6) 它能拍摄更高分辨率的图像
using the same scanning type camera used in Corona.
使用与日冕相同的扫描式相机
However the performance of this wasn't particularly good
然而性能并不是特别好
and it only flew three times before being superseded by another program known as Gambit.
而它只飞了三次就被另一个叫策略(KH-7)的项目所取代
And while this also launched from Vandenberg, it launched on board an Atlas-Agena
而这个项目虽然也是从范登堡发射的 但它是用宇宙神-阿金纳火箭进行的发射
and it was developed and run by the National Reconnaissance Office.
而且它是由美国国家侦察局开发和运行的
Also at the same time there was another program called Samos which was developed by the US air force.
同时还有另一个叫萨摩斯的项目 它是由美国空军开发的
Apparently they were in much more of a hurry
很明显 这个项目对图像采集时间的要求更加紧迫
so that satellite would actually develop the film on orbit
那么这个卫星会在轨冲洗胶卷
and then it would scan it and send it back down to Earth electronically.
接着把胶卷扫描 并以电子的方式将其传回地球
It would also ship the stuff via the return bucket technique.
它也同样可以用返回桶的技术把胶卷快递运送回来
Apparently the quality of the imagery wasn't really worth the extra effort
不过很显然 图像的质量并不值得额外的努力去回收它的胶卷桶
and so the project never went very far.
所以这个项目一直没有走得很远
However the same camera design and the developing and the scanning
然而 同样的相机设计 显影和扫描技术
would be taken to the moon for the lunar orbiter project
将被送上月球 用于月球轨道器项目
where of course it was much harder to get a physical roll of film back from the moon.
当然 这是因为从月球上取回一卷实体胶卷的方法要难得多
But I guess the air force continued in the spy game for a little while
但我想空军在间谍游戏中继续玩了一段时间
because they proposed the manned orbiting laboratory KH-10
因为他们提议建造载人轨道实验室KH-10
that would be a Gemini spacecraft
这会发射一个双子座飞船
and the crew after getting into orbit would open up a hatch in the heat shield
在入轨后 乘员会打开隔热板的舱门
and climb into a lab where they would be able to control cameras
并爬进实验室 在那里 他们会去控制相机
and point them at target of opportunity
并在目标的拍摄窗口将相机指向目标并成像
and therefore respond in real time and hopefully get better intelligence.
因此就可以实时地反应并成像 希望能得到更好的情报
That never flew but it was certainly a fascinating project.
虽然这个项目没能成真 但这确实令人着迷
The Gambit would evolve into the Hexagon which would have a monster of four return buckets.
策略项目后来演变成了六角形项目(KH-9) 它有一个由四个返回桶组成的怪物
And this would fly from 1971 right up till 1986.
这个项目从1971年一直飞到1986年
It was declassified in 2011 but I believe that's the last of the large photographic spy satellites.
它在2011年解密 但我相信那是最后一颗大型(胶片)成像间谍卫星
After that they all went to electro-optical.
此后 它们都转为电子光学卫星
And that was the KH-11 Kennen and its successors which are still heavily classified.
而那是KH-11洞悉以及它的后续卫星 这些仍处于高度机密的状态
Although we do know they share a lot in common with the Hubble Space Telescope.
尽管我们知道它们与哈勃太空望远镜有很多共同之处
And two more were donated to NASA.
而且还有另外两台捐赠给了NASA
One of which is being used to make the WFIRST telescope.
其中一个被用来制造罗曼空间天文台
But yes that's 60 years since spy satellites as we know it began.
但是 是的 距离间谍卫星的出现已经过去了60年
And this is the design of the bucket that the CIA used to bring Corona back from space.
而这张图里的就是CIA从太空中回收日冕卫星的桶的设计
And hopefully I won't get demonetised for saying this.
希望我不会因为做了这个视频而被和谐
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]